<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wkumari-dnsop-multiple-responses-03"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="RFC5011 Security Considerations ">Security
    Considerations for RFC5011 Publishers.</title>

    <author fullname="Wes Hardaker" initials="W." surname="Hardaker">
      <organization>Parsons, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 382</street>

          <city>Davis, CA</city>

          <code>95617</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ietf@hardakers.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="July" year="2016"/>

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>dnsop</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the minimum requirements which a
      publisher of a zone must wait before using a new DNSKEY
      advertised using the RFC5011 DNSKEY rollover process.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>RFC5011 <xref target="rfc5011"> defines a mechanism by which
      DNSSEC validators can extend there list of trust anchors when
      they've seen a new key.  However, RFC5011 [intentionally]
      provides no feedback to publishers of DNSKEYs about how long
      they must wait before such a new key is actually usable.
      Because of this lack of guidance, DNSSEC publishers may derive
      incorrect assumptions about safe usage of the RFC5011 process.
      This document describes the minimum security requirements from a
      publishers point of view and is indented to compliment the
      guidance offered in RFC5011, which is designed to solely
      represent the Validating Resolvers point of view.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Background">
      <t>The RFC5011 process outlines a timed process by which a
      Validating Resolver may accept a newly published KSK as a trust
      anchor for validating future DNSSEC signed records.  This
      document augments that information with additional constraints,
      as required from the DNSKEY publication point of view.  Note
      that it does not define any other operational guidance or
      recommendations about the RFC5011 process from a publication
      point of view and restricts itself to solely the security
      ramifications of switching to a new key too soon.  Failure of a
      DNSKEY publisher to follow the minimum recommendations
      associated with this draft will result in potential
      denial-of-service attack opportunities against validating
      resolvers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t><list style="hanging">
	      <t hangText="foo"> bar
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Timing associated with RFC5011 processing">
	    <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Denial of Service Attack Considerations">
      <t>If an attacker is able to provide a RFC5011 validating engine
      with past responses, such as when it is in-path or able to
      otherwise perform any number of cache poising attacks, the
      following timeline depicts an attack where the subscribing
      RFC5011-compliant validator will be left without an appropriate
      DNSKEY trust anchor.</t>

      <section title="Numerical Concrete Attack Example">
	      <t>These assumptions are used in the example scenario within
	      this section. 

	      <list style="hanging">
		      <t hangText="TTL (all records)">1 day</t>
		      <t hangText="RRSIG Signature Validity">10 days</t>
		      <t hangText="Zone resigned every">1 day</t>
	      </list>
	      </t>

	      <t>Given these assumptions, then the following sequence of
	      events depicts how a Trust Anchor Publisher (XXX: TERM!) which
	      waits for only the RFC5011 hold time timer length of 30 days
	      subjects its users to a potential Denial of Service attack.  The
	      timing schedule listed below is based on a new key being
	      published at T+0, and where all numbers in this sequence refer to
	      days before and after such an event.  Thus, T-1 is the day
	      before the introduction of the new key, and T+15 is the 15th day
	      after the key was introduced into the zone being discussed..</t>

	      <t>In this dialog, we consider two keys being published:
	      <list style="hanging">
		      <t hangText="Kold">The older key being replaced.</t>
		      <t hangText="Knew">The new key being transitioned into
		      active use, through the RFC5011 process.</t>
	      </list> </t>

	      <section title="Timing Breakdown">

		      <p>The following series of steps depicts the timeline in
		      which an attack occurs that foils the publisher of a new
		      key who revokes the old key too quickly.</p>
		      
		      <list style="hanging">
			      <t hangText="T-1">Last signatures published that
			      only signs Kold.</t>
		      </list>
	      </section>
      </section
</section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document contains no IANA considerations.</t>


    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document, in its entirety, is solely about the security
      considerations with respect to the publisher of RFC5011 trust
      anchors / keys.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5011 ?>
    </references>

    <!--
        <references title="Informative References">
        </references>
    -->

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>None yet</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
